Guide to the Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories 2018.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with Siraj Wahhaj, February 19, 2018; 2018.006.06
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community policing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Imams (Mosque officers) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- New York; Muslim converts -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid Muhammad 7C (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Muhammad Mosque No. 7C (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Elijah Muhammad, 1897-1975; Farrakhan, Louis; Muhammad, Warith Deen, 1933-2008; Wahhaj, Siraj
- Oral History Interview with Abdul Rasheed Abdullah, March 10, 2018; 2018.006.07
  Abdul Rasheed Abdullah was born in 1952 in Brooklyn. He joined the Nation of Islam and married his wife in the 1970s, and was involved in Muslim communities in both Queens and Brooklyn. In 1984, his son received a scholarship to study in Sudan through the Al-Madrasa Al-Islamiya school in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. The family relocated and Abdullah spent his time in Sudan studying Sufism. After returning to New York, he taught as a licensed Sufi shaikh in a zawiyah in Brooklyn. He also attended Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah and Masjid At-Taqwa, both in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, and was the head of the Islamic studies department at Masjid Khalifah's Clara Muhammad School.
  In this interview, Abdul Rasheed Abdullah discusses his childhood in Brooklyn and Queens, his exposure to the Five Percent Nation as an adolescent, and his embrace of the Nation of Islam while serving an eighteen-month prison sentence. He speaks about his participation in the Nation of Islam-affiliated Muhammad Mosque No. 7B in the Corona neighborhood of Queens and Muhammad Mosque No. 7C in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn; his reaction to Elijah Muhammad's death in 1975; and his subsequent exploration of Masjid At-Taqwa in Bedford-Stuyvesant and Yasin Masjid in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. He expands on studying Sufism in Sudan and teaching as a licensed Sufi shaikh after his return to New York. He also talks at length about his wife's religious convictions and support; his father's embrace of Islam; and his friendship with Imam Siraj Wahhaj (interviewed for this collection on February 19, 2018). Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- New York; Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- New York; Black power -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Civil rights movements -- United States -- 20th century; Islamic religious education; Mosques -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim converts from Christianity -- New York (State) -- New York; Muslim educators; Muslim families -- New York (State) -- New York; Prisoners -- Religious life -- United States; Religious education of children -- New York (State) -- New York; Spirituality -- Muslims; Sufism; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Corona (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Sudan; Five Percent Nation; Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Muhammad Mosque No. 7B (Queens, New York, N.Y.); Muhammad Mosque No. 7C (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Yasin Masjid (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Abdullah, Abdul Rasheed; Wahhaj, Siraj
- Oral History Interview with Zein Rimawi, March 13, 2018; 2018.006.08
  Zein Rimawi was born in 1954 near the city of Jerusalem during a period of changing political boundaries. After studying engineering in Lebanon and East Germany, he immigrated to the United States in the early 1980s. He settled in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn and he co-founded both the Islamic Society of Bay Ridge and the Al-Noor School, the latter of which his children attended.
  In this interview, Zein Rimawi discusses growing up in a village near Jerusalem, studying engineering in East Germany, and then immigrating to the United States. He addresses his personal experiences with cultural assimilation in East Germany and in the United States, and also speaks extensively about the importance of voting and political activism within his community. In addition, he touches on the value of interfaith celebrations, his relationships with his children, and his personal philosophy regarding work and charity. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamic religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Israel-Arab War, 1967; Muslims -- Suffrage -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Palestinian Arabs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Germany (East); Israel; Palestine; Al-Noor School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Islamic Center of Bay Ridge (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); El-Yateem, Khader; Rimawi, Zein
- Oral History Interview with Amer Abdelrasoul, March 20, 2018
  Amer Abdelrasoul was born in 1991 in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn. He attended the Al-Noor School before moving to Palestine for high school. After returning to Brooklyn, he married his wife and co-founded the Freedom Dabka Group, which performs the traditional Arab dabka folk dance.
  In this interview, Amer Abdelrasoul discusses his experiences growing up as a Palestinian American, including attending elementary school at the Al-Noor School in Brooklyn and high school in Palestine. He also talks extensively about his involvement in dabka dance, especially regarding his founding of and continued involvement with the Freedom Dabka Group. In addition, he touches on his cultural and religious values, his arranged marriage to his wife, and the conflict he feels between traditional Muslim teachings and his passion for dance. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Arranged marriage -- United States; Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Folk dancing, Arab -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam and the performing arts -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Palestinian Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Israel; Palestine; Abdelrasoul, Amer; Al-Noor School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freedom Dabka Group
- Oral History Interview with Mohammad Razvi, March 21, 2018; 2018.006.10
  Mohammad Razvi was born in 1971 in Pakistan. He immigrated to the United States as a small child in the late 1970s, and his family settled in the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn. He started several businesses in the Midwood neighborhood of Brooklyn following his marriage to his wife, and founded the Council of Peoples Organization (COPO) after the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001. Through COPO, engagement with law enforcement agencies, and participation in research regarding hate crimes, he worked to provide support to Muslim and immigrant communities.
  In this interview, Mohammad Razvi discusses his upbringing in the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn, with particular emphasis on the role his family-owned businesses in the Midwood neighborhood of Brooklyn have played in providing support to the local Pakistani community. He talks about founding Council of Peoples Organization (COPO) to protect immigrant and Muslim communities from harassment, arrests, and deportation following the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001. He also elaborates about his work with law enforcement agencies to improve their approach to communities COPO serves and his research about hate crimes. In addition, he speaks about his childhood friendships, his marriage to his wife, and the importance of interfaith and multicultural friendships in both his personal and professional lives. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Bullying -- Religious aspects -- Muslims; Cultural competence -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Faith-based human services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Grocery trade -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hate crimes -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hurricane Sandy, 2012; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Pakistani Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Racial profiling in law enforcement -- New York (State) -- Kings County; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Midwood (New York, N.Y.); Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Council of Peoples Organization (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Punjab Grocery and Deli (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; Razvi, Mohammad
- Oral History Interview with Zeinab Bader, March 23, 2018; 2018.006.11
  Zeinab Bader was born in 1956 in Tyre, Lebanon, and immigrated to the United States with her husband and infant daughter in 1980. After settling in New York, she volunteered for several years as a teacher in an Arabic school run by the Palestinian Women's Association of New York. She resigned from the position in 1991 and spent several years raising her children, and then pursued work as a health insurance specialist. She also served on the board of Arab American Association of New York and organized their Mother's Day celebrations for several years.
  In this interview, Zeinab Bader discusses her upbringing in Lebanon, touching on her family's religious convictions and her sister's death in childbirth. She elaborates broadly on the impact of the Lebanese Civil War on her family, including the deaths of two of her brothers, threats to her own safety, and its role in her family accepting her betrothal to her Palestinian husband. She also speaks about her immigration to the United States, raising her five children in Brooklyn, and her involvement in their religious and secular educations. She talks about her own work to empower Arab American women, especially through civic activism, access to family and mental health care, and special events. In addition, she addresses her own religious convictions and practices, battle with breast cancer, and involvement in the Arab American Association of New York. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Child health insurance -- New York (State); Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Interethnic marriage -- Lebanon; Islamic religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Lebanese -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Lebanon -- History -- Civil War, 1975-1990; Mother's Day -- New York (State) -- New York; Muslims -- Suffrage -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women's health services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Tyre (Lebanon); Arab American Association of New York; Child Health Plus B (N.Y.); NYU Langone Medical Center; NYU Lutheran Medical Center; Bader, Zeinab; Palestinian Women's Association (New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Sarah Aly, April 5, 2018
  This interview is restricted.
- Oral History Interview with Marion Sedorowitz, April 11, 2018; 2018.006.13
  Marion Sedorowitz was born in 1954 in Brooklyn and was raised in Hauppauge, New York. As a child, she attended the Brooklyn Moslem Mosque in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, which had been founded by her Tatar community following their immigration from Eastern Europe throughout the early 1900s. She briefly worked as a pharmacist after earning a bachelor and a master's degree in pharmacy from St. John's University in Queens, and then went on to become a consultant for the creation and management of electronic medical records. As an adult, she also became involved in the management of the Brooklyn Moslem Mosque, including serving as treasurer on the board with her niece, Alyssa Haughwout (interviewed for this collection on April 25, 2018) and planning the mosque's centennial celebration.
  In this interview, Marion Sedorowitz discusses her family, especially regarding their traditional Tatar cooking, immigration to the United States, religious traditions, and involvement with the Brooklyn Moslem Mosque in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. She expands on her own experiences with the mosque, including her successful efforts to remove the curtain preventing women from seeing the imam during prayers, her organization of the centennial celebration, and generational friction within the board about modernized outreach and records-keeping. In addition, she talks about her childhood experiences in the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn, work in the medical field, and concerns about Islamophobia. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Cooking, Tatar -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Special events -- Planning -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Tatars -- History; Tatars -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Technology and older people -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); American Mohammedan Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Haughwout, Alyssa; Sedorowitz, Marion
- Oral History Interview with Jo Ann Benoit, April 14, 2018; 2018.006.14
  Jo Ann Benoit was born in 1975 in Brooklyn. She spent most of her childhood being raised by her grandmother in Haiti, with regular trips to visit her mother in Brooklyn. She moved back to Brooklyn permanently following the 1991 Haitian coup d'état, where she completed her last two years of high school. While attending Pace University in Manhattan, she worked as an interpretor and English language teacher for Haitian refugees. Her passion for education continued throughout her adulthood, leading her to work as both a teacher and a school administrator. Coursework for one of her graduate degrees in education inspired her initial interest in Islam, which she embraced in 1999.
  In this interview, Jo Ann Benoit discusses her childhood, including growing up in Haiti, attending a Catholic school there, and moving to Brooklyn as a teenager. She also talks about her passion for education and community activism, especially regarding her work as an English language teacher, interpreter, and school administrator. She elaborates about her Muslim faith, including her initial exposure to Islam through graduate level coursework, embracing Islam, observance of Muslim customs and traditions, and raising two children in an interfaith marriage. In addition, she speaks about having her portrait taken for an article in Essence Magazine. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Catholic schools -- Haiti; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community activists; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Haiti; Haitian Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Interfaith families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim converts from Christianity -- New York (State) -- New York; Refugees -- New York (State) -- New York; Haitian Women for Haitian Refugees (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Shahana Hanif, April 17, 2018; 2018.006.15
  Shahana Hanif was born in 1991 in Brooklyn. She was raised in the Bangladeshi community in the Kensington neighborhood of Brooklyn. After a health crisis as a teenager led to a diagnosis of lupus, she went on to earn a bachelor's degree in women's and gender studies from Brooklyn College. While there, she became involved in intersectional activism and community organizing, especially with the Committee Against Anti-Asian Violence (CAAAV) and Naree Shongothok: Bangladeshi Women Organizing for Social Change. She also worked as Director of Organizing and Community Engagement for New York City council member Brad Lander.
  In this interview, Shahana Hanif discusses growing up in a Bangladeshi American family in the Kensington neighborhood of Brooklyn, including her relationship with her sister, the impact strict gender roles had on their religious educations and social lives, receiving a diagnosis of lupus as a teenager, and her subsequent navigation of health and accessibility limitations. She also talks about her exploration of intersectionality and activism in college, especially regarding her disability, religion, and race. In addition, she speaks about internet activism and specific organizations and causes she became involved in, especially Naree O Shongothok, the Muslim Writers Collective, the Kensington Stewards, and a local ladies' club. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Bangladeshi Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Communities -- Religious aspects -- Muslims; Health services accessibility -- New York (State) -- New York; Internet and activism; Intersectionality (Sociology); Islam -- Prayers and devotions; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- New York; Lupus -- Patients -- New York (State) -- Kings County; People with disabilities -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Shelters for the homeless -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Kensington (New York, N.Y.); Church Avenue Merchants Block Association, Inc. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Global Spiritual Life (New York University); Kensington Stewards (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Muslim Student Association (Brooklyn College); Muslim Writers Collective; Naree O Shongothok: Bangladeshi Women Organizing for Social Change; The Kensington Family Shelter (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Hanif, Shahana; Lander, Brad
- Oral History Interview with Alyssa Haughwout, April 25, 2018; 2018.006.16
  Alyssa Haughwout was born in 1984 in Queens and raised in Long Island. Her family frequently traveled into the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn throughout her childhood to attend their Tatar community's Brooklyn Moslem Mosque, which had been founded following the group's immigration from Eastern Europe throughout the early 1900s. She first served on the mosque's board with her aunt, Marion Sedorowitz (interviewed for this collection on April 11, 2018) while working toward a master's degree in art and design education from Pratt Institute in Brooklyn. She eventually became the board's vice president as well as the caretaker of the mosque.
  In this interview, Alyssa Haughwout discusses her community's Tatar heritage and Muslim faith, especially regarding their founding of the Brooklyn Moslem Mosque in 1907, unique language and religious practices, concerns about assimilation, and recent shifts from their traditional handling of gender roles. She also talks about her own relationship with her Muslim identity, including her deeper exploration of Islam in college, work as caretaker of the mosque's building and historical artifacts, concerns about Islamophobia, and experiences as a white Muslim woman. In addition, she touches on generational friction within the board over modernization of the mosque, her family's deep roots in the community, and her appreciation of interfaith celebrations. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Building management -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Communities -- Religious aspects -- Muslims; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamic education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim women -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Ramadan -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Tatar Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Tatar language -- Dialects; Technology and older people -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); American Mohammedan Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Haughwout, Alyssa; Sedorowitz, Marion
- Oral History Interview with Abdul Rehman, May 3, 2018
  Abdul Rehman was born in 1944 near Mirpur, Kashmir. He earned a medical degree from Dow Medical College in Karachi, Pakistan. After immigrating to the United States in 1968, he completed his internship at Evangelical Deaconess Hospital in Detroit, Michigan and his residency at Brooklyn Hospital Center in the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn. He practiced internal medicine in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and took on leadership roles within Brooklyn's medical community, including serving as president of the Medical Society of the County of Kings.
  In this interview, Abdul Rehman describes growing up near Mirpur, Kashmir (also considered part of Pakistan), particularly regarding his family and medical education. He expands on his immigration to the United States; settling in Detroit, Michigan and Brooklyn, New York; and growth of Brooklyn's Muslim communities since he arrived. He speaks extensively about practicing medicine in Pakistan, Michigan, and Brooklyn; his research on sickle cell anemia; and his tenure as president of the Medical Society of the County of Kings. He also talks about his marriage to his wife and recites an excerpt of original Urdu poetry. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Azad Kashmir (Pakistan); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Detroit (Mich.); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Karachi (Pakistan); Food -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Immigrants -- United States; Kashmiri (South Asian people); Marriage -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Medical education; Muslim physicians -- United States; Pakistan -- Emigration and immigration; Religion in the workplace -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sickle cell anemia; Urdu poetry; Medical Society of the County of Kings (Kings County, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Mohammed Hashem, May 10, 2018; 2018.006.18
  Mohammed Hashem was born in 1957 in East Pakistan (now Bangladesh). He immigrated to the United States as a young man and settled in the Kensington neighborhood of Brooklyn. He pursued work in the construction industry, eventually starting his own company. He also co-founded the Bangladesh Muslim Center and Islamic School, where he served as the board's treasurer, secretary, and president.
  In this interview, Mohammed Hashem discusses his experiences with the Kensington neighborhood of Brooklyn's Bangladeshi community, including his co-founding and continued involvement with the growing Bangladesh Muslim Center and Islamic School; the benefits of the community's positive relationships with other local religious groups, elected officials, and law enforcement; and the role of traditional food in facilitating social relationships. He also speaks about his immediate and extended family, many of whom have also settled in Kensington. In addition, Hashem talks about the social and political state of modern Bangladesh as well as his memories of living in Bangladesh during the Bangladesh Independence War in 1971. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.